<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook book.xsd ">
	<chapter>
		<title>1 Integration concepts</title>
		<para>
		DHIS2 is an open platform and its implementers are active
		contributors to interoperability initiatives, such as openHIE.
		The DHIS2 application database is designed with flexibility in
		mind. Data structures such as data elements, organisation units,
		forms and user roles can be defined completely freely through
		the application user interface. This makes it possible for the
		system to be adapted to a multitude of local contexts and
		use-cases. DHIS2 supports many requirements for routine data
		capture and analysis emerging in country implementations. It
		also makes it possible for DHIS2 to serve as a basic management
		system in domains such as <markup>logistics, laboratory management and
		finance</markup>.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>1.1	Integration and interoperability</title>
			<para>Based on its platform approach, DHIS2 is able to receive and host data from different data sources and share it to other systems and reporting mechanisms. An important distinction of integration concepts is the difference between data integration and systems interoperability:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						When talking about <emphasis>integration</emphasis>, we think about
						the process of making different information
						systems appear as one, making data available to
						all relevant users as well as the harmonization
						of definitions and dimensions so that it is
						possible to combine the data in useful ways.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						A related concept is <emphasis>interoperability</emphasis>, which is one strategy 
						to achieve integration. 
						We consider DHIS2interoperable with other software applications because of its capability to exchange data. 
						For example, DHIS2 and <markup>OpenMRS</markup> are interoperable, because they allow to share data definitions and data with each other.  
						Interoperability depends on standards for data formats, interfaces and codes and terminologies. 
						These would ideally be internationally balloted standards, but in practice may also consist of de facto standards  and other more local agreements within a particular context.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>To say that something is integrated, then, means that they share something, and that they are available from one place, while interoperability usually means that they are able to do this sharing electronically. 
			DHIS2 is often used as an integrated data warehouse, since it contains (aggregate) data from various sources, such as 
			<markup>Mother and Child health, Malaria program, census data, and data on stocks and human resources</markup>. 
			These data sources share the same platform, DHIS2, and are available all from the same place. 
			These subsystems are thus considered integrated into one system.
			</para>
			<para>Interoperability in addition will integrate data sources from other software applications. 
			For example, if census data is stored in a specialized 
			<markup>civil registry or in a vital events system</markup>, 
			interoperability between this database and DHIS2 would mean that census data would also be be accessible in DHIS2.
			</para>
			<para>Finally, the most basic integration activity, that is not always taken into account in the interoperability discussion, is the possibility to integratedata from existing paper systems or parallel vertical systems into DHIS2. 
			Data will be entered directly into DHIS2 without passing through a different software application. 
			This process is based on creating consistent indicator definitions and can already greatly reduce fragmentation andenhance data analysis through an integrated data repository.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>1.2	Objectives of integration</title>
			<para>In most countries we find many different, <emphasis>isolated</emphasis> health information systems, causing many information management challenges. Public Health Information System have seen an explosive and often uncoordinated growth over the last years. Modern information technology makes it less costly to implement ICT4D solutions, which can lead to a high diversity of solutions. A staggering example was the mHealth moratorium declaration of Uganda´s MoH in 2012, as a reaction to an avalanche of around 50 mHealth solutions that were implemented within the course of a few years.   Most of these solutions were standalone approaches that did not share their data with the national systems and rarely were developed beyond pilot status.</para>
			<para>This may lead to the conclusion, that all systems should be connected or that <emphasis>interoperability is an objective</emphasis> in itself. However DHIS2 is often employed in contexts, where infrastructure is weak, and where resources to run even basic systems reliably are scarce. Fragmentation is a serious problem in this context, however interoperability approaches can only resolve some of the fragmentation problems - and often interoperability approaches result in an additional layer of complexity.</para>
			<example>
				<title>Example: Complexity of Logistics solutions in Ghana</title>
				<para>In the area of Logistics or Supply Chain Management, often a multitude of parallel, overlapping or competing software solutions can be found in a single country. As identified in a JSI study in 2012, eighteen (18!) different software tools were documented as being used within the public health supply chain in Ghana alone.</para>
			</example>
			<para>
				<superscript>1</superscript>
				A de facto standard is something which has wide
				acceptance and usage but not necessarily formally
				balloted in a standards development organisation.				
				<superscript>2</superscript>
				<link>http://www.ictworks.org/2012/02/22/ugandan-mhealth-moratorium-good-thing/</link>
			</para>
			<para>Systems interoperability therefore seems as one possibility to remove fragmentation and redundancies and give public health officers a concise and balanced picture from available data sources. However the effort of connecting many redundant software solutions would be very high and therefore seems questionable. In a first step, focus should be on reducing the number of parallel systems and identifying the most relevant systems, afterwards these relevant systems can be integrated.</para>
			<para>
				On this background, we want to define the major
				objectives of DHIS2 integration approaches:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para><emphasis>Calculation of indicators:</emphasis> Many indicators are based on numerators and denominators from different data sources. Examples include mortality rates, including some mortality data as numerator and population data as denominator, staff coverage and staff workload rates (human resource data, and population and headcount data), immunization rates, and the like. For the calculation, you need both the numerator and denominator data, and they should thus be integrated into a single data warehouse. The more data sources that are integrated, the more indicators can be generated from the central repository.</para>
						<para><emphasis>Reducemanual processing and entering of data:</emphasis> With different data at the same place, there is no need to manually extract and process indicators, or re-enter data into the data warehouse. Especially interoperability between systems of different data types (such as patient registers and aggregate data warehouse) allows software for subsystems to both calculate and share data electronically. This reduces the amount of manual steps involved in data processing, which increases data quality.</para>
						<para><emphasis>Reduce redundancies:</emphasis> Often overlapping and redundant data is being captured by the various parallel systems. For instance will HIV/AIDS related data elements be captured both by both multiple general counselling and testing programs and the specialized HIV/AIDS program. Harmonizing the data collection tools of such programs will reduce the total workload of the end users. This implies that such data sources can be integrated into DHIS2 and harmonized with the existing data elements, which involves both data entry and data analysis requirements.</para>
						<para>Improve <emphasis>organizational</emphasis> aspects: If all data can be handled by one unit in the ministry of health, instead of various subsystems maintained by the several health programs, this one unit can be professionalized. With staff which sole responsibility is data management, processing, and analysis, more specialized skills can be developed and the information handling be rationalized.</para>
						<para>Integration of <emphasis>vertical programs</emphasis>: The typical government health domain has a lot of existing players and systems. An integrated database containing data from various sources becomes more valuable and useful than fragmented and isolated ones. For instance when analysis of epidemiological data is combined with specialized <markup>HIV/AIDS, TB, financial and human resource data</markup>, or when <markup>immunization</markup> is combined with <markup>logistics/stock</markup> data, it will give a more complete picture of the situation. </para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			<para>
			DHIS2 can help streamlining and <emphasis>simplifying system architecture</emphasis>, following questions such as:What is the objective of the integration effort? Can DHIS2 help reduce the number of systems? Can an DHIS2 integration help provide relevant management information at a lower cost,  at at higher speed and with a better data quality than the existing systems? More practical information on defining these objectives can be found in <link>STEP 1 of the 6-Step implementation guideline</link>.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>1.3	Health information exchange</title>
			<para>Since there are different use-cases for health information, there are different types of software applications functioning within the health sector. We use the term architecture for health information to describe a plan or overview of the various software applications, their specific uses and data connections. The architecture functions as a plan to coordinate the development and interoperability of various subsystems within the larger health information system. It is advisable to develop a plan that covers all components, including the areas that are currently not running any software, to be able to adequately see the requirements in terms of data sharing. These requirements should then be part of specifications for the software once it is developed or procured.</para>
			<para>The <emphasis>openhealth information exchange (openHIE)</emphasis>  is an interoperable interpretation of this architecture, with an HMIS or DHIS2 often assuming a significant role in it.The openHIE framework has been developed with a clear focus on countries in low resource settings, through the participation of several institutions and development partners, including the Oslo HISP program.</para>
			<para>
				The schematic overview below shows the main elements of
				the openHIE framework, containing a component layer, an
				interoperability services layer and external systems.
				<figure>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref=""></imagedata><!--Please provide the reference to image in fileref attribute-->
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</para>
			<para>The openHIE component layer covers meta or reference data (Terminology, Clients, Facilities), Personal data (Staff, Patient History) and national health statistics. The purpose is to ensure the availability of the same meta data in all systems that participate in the corresponding data exchange (e.g. indicator definitions, facility naming, coding and classification). In some cases, like the case of the Master Facility Registry, the data may also be used to provide information to the general public through a web portal. While the interoperability layer ensures data brokerage between the different systems, the external systems layer contains several sub-systems, many at point of service level, with often overlapping functional range.</para>
			<para>There are different approaches to define an eHealth architecture. In the context of this DHIS2 guideline, we distinguish between approaches based on a 1:1 connection versus approaches based on an n:n connection (many-to-many).</para>
			<section> 
				<title>1.3.1	1:1 integration</title> <!--No subsection element in DTD, thats why using section element-->
				<para>In many countries a national HMIS is often the first system to be rolled out to a large number of facilities and to manage a large number of data on a monthly or quarterly basis. When countries start to develop their health system architecture further, DHIS2 often will be connected to some other systems. This connection is done directly through a simple script, which automates a data transfer.</para>
				<para>We talk of a 1:1 connection because it is limited to two systems. In the case of an LMIS/HMIS integration, one LMIS (e.g. openLMIS as is the case in Tanzania) will transfer data to DHIS2 as defined in the script. In case a second logistics system would want to transfer data to DHIS2 (e.g. commodity data for a specific disease program), a second script would have to written, to perform this task. These two scripts would then run independently from another, resulting in two separate 1:1 connections.</para>
				<para>This hands-on approach often represents a first step and is one of the most common use cases on the way to an interoperable openHIE architecture.</para>
			</section>
			<section> 
				<title>1.3.2	n:nintegration</title> <!--No subsection element in DTD, thats why using section element-->
				<para>A different approach is based on placing a purpose-built software to serve as an <emphasis>interoperability layer</emphasis> or BUS approach, managing the data transfer between possibly several  systems on either side (n:n). This could be the case if for example you wanted to collect stock level data through different LMIS applications, and then share it to a central warehouse LMIS, the HMIS and some vertical disease programs system. The openHIE reference software to assume this role is Jembi openHIM, but Grameen Motech has also been used for this purpose as discussed below.</para>
				<para>While this approach may result in a higher initial effort, it promises to make further integration project easier, because the interoperability layer is being alimented with definitions and mappings that can be re-used for connecting the next systems.</para>
				<para>In practice, there are certain challenges to this approach. It takes a considerable effort of qualified resources to activate APIs and with each new release of any involved system, data flows required re-testing and if necessary adaptations. Also, to be successful these implementation projects typically have to go through a series of <link>complex steps</link>, such as the agreement on an interoperability approach embedded in the national eHealth strategy, the definition of data standards and sustainable maintenance structure, and attaining a stakeholder consensus on data ownership and sharing policies.<superscript>1</superscript> There can be some long term consequences when data and systems are knitted together - it creates new roles, jobs, categories of labour which didn't exist before and may not have been planned for (metadata governance, complex system administration, boundary negotiators, etc.).</para>
				<example>
					<title>Example: Grameen DHIS2/CommCare middle layer in Senegal</title>
					<para>In a <markup>MIS/LMIS implementation in Senegal</markup>, Grameen MOTECH serves as technical middle layer between an LMIS (CommCare) and DHIS2, allowing to define data mapping, transformation rules and data quality checks. The interface is set-up to transfers data from CommCare Supply to DHIS2 whenever data is saved into a CommCare form at facilities. For each commodity, data on consumption, available stock, losses and stock-out data is transferred from CommCare to DHIS2. </para>
					<para>The higher initial investment of the Senegal approach hints towards a more ambitious long-term system architecture, foreseeing that the <emphasis>Grameen Motech</emphasis> platform may in future serve to accommodate further interoperability task. However we do not see any of the country activities tightly embedded in a text-book eHealth architecture, which would clearly define areas of priority, leading systems for each priority and the relations and resulting APIs between these different components. One may argue that interoperability projects are built on a weak foundation if there is no previous consensus on an architectural master plan. On the other hand it is also valuable to allow system initiatives to organically develop, as long as they are rooted in well-founded country needs.</para>
				</example>
				
			</section>
		</section>
	</chapter>
</book>
